<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-28T18:49:50+00:00</updated><id>https://shahrajabian.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Mahdi Shahrajabian&apos;s Website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Control Systems Design</title><link href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2024/Paradigm-Shift-CSD/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Control Systems Design"/><published>2024-11-11T10:00:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-11T10:00:10+00:00</updated><id>https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2024/Paradigm-Shift-CSD</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2024/Paradigm-Shift-CSD/"><![CDATA[<p>This diagram highlights the different eras in control systems development, showcasing the key ideas and challenges addressed during each phase. As our systems have grown increasingly complex—dealing with variable dynamic characteristics, strong nonlinearities, heavy coupling, unclear mechanisms and mathematically un-modellable—the limitations of existing control theories have become more apparent. This complexity makes modeling a daunting task, underscoring the urgent need for innovative control methods.</p> <p>The content of the diagram is primarily inspired by concepts from Prof. Ali Khaki-Sedigh’s book, An Introduction to Data-Driven Control Systems (John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2023)</p> <p>Download the high-resolution file of the diagram from <a href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/assets/img/Paradigm_Shift_in_Control_Systems_Design.png">here</a>.</p> <p>Download the pdf file of the diagram with reference links to the control methods from <a href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/assets/pdf/Paradigm_Shift_in_Control_Systems_Design.pdf">here</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Paradigm_Shift_in_Control_Systems_Design-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Paradigm_Shift_in_Control_Systems_Design-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Paradigm_Shift_in_Control_Systems_Design-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Paradigm_Shift_in_Control_Systems_Design.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Paradigm Shift in Control Systems Design" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption text-center">Paradigm Shift in Control Systems Design</div> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="control"/><category term="control"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Paradigm Shift in Control Systems Design]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Control Methods</title><link href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2024/control-methods/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Control Methods"/><published>2024-09-01T10:00:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T10:00:10+00:00</updated><id>https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2024/control-methods</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2024/control-methods/"><![CDATA[<p>Control methods in control theory can be classified into several categories based on various criteria, each reflecting different approaches to managing dynamic systems.</p> <p>One of the primary distinctions is between model-based and model-free control strategies. Model-based control relies on mathematical representations of the system, utilizing models that describe the dynamics and behavior of the system under various conditions. This approach allows for precise predictions and adjustments based on the system’s expected performance. In contrast, model-free control does not require an explicit model of the system. Instead, it focuses on using real-time data or learning from interactions with the environment, making it particularly useful in situations where the system is too complex to model accurately or where the model is unknown. Moreover, there are new control methods that utilize the nominal model of the system while also incorporating real-time data to enhance the performance of the control system by integrating both model-based and data-driven approaches.</p> <p>Furthermore, model-based control methods can also be categorized as linear or nonlinear. Linear control methods are based on linear models that describe the system’s behavior, which simplifies the analysis and design of control systems. These methods are often easier to implement and understand, making them suitable for a wide range of applications where system dynamics can be approximated as linear. On the other hand, nonlinear control methods are designed to handle systems exhibiting complex behaviors that cannot be accurately captured by linear equations. Nonlinear control techniques are essential for managing systems with inherent nonlinearities, such as saturation, hysteresis, or varying operational conditions, and they often require more sophisticated mathematical tools and approaches.</p> <p>A summary of the different control methods (control strategies) is shown in the following figure. It is worth noting that there are various combinations of these control methods found in the literature.</p> <p>Download the high-resolution file of the diagram from <a href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/assets/img/ControlMethods.png">here</a>.</p> <p>Download the pdf file of the diagram with reference links to the control methods from <a href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/assets/pdf/Control_Methods.pdf">here</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ControlMethods-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ControlMethods-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ControlMethods-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ControlMethods.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Classification of Control Methods in Control Theory" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption text-center">Classification of Control Methods in Control Theory</div> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="control"/><category term="control"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Classification of Control Methods in Control Theory]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Model-Based Design</title><link href="https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2022/MBD/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Model-Based Design"/><published>2022-08-10T10:00:10+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-10T10:00:10+00:00</updated><id>https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2022/MBD</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shahrajabian.github.io/blog/2022/MBD/"><![CDATA[<p>Model-Based Design (MBD) in control systems is a systematic approach that utilizes mathematical models to design, simulate, and validate control algorithms and systems.</p> <p>The process begins with defining requirements and creating a mathematical representation of the system, enabling engineers to analyze its dynamics effectively. Model-based control algorithms are then developed and tested through model-in-the-loop simulations, often using tools like MATLAB/Simulink, to evaluate critical performance metrics such as stability and response time. Once validated, automatic code generation facilitates the implementation of these algorithms on hardware. This is followed by Software-in-the-Loop (SIL), Processor-in-the-Loop (PIL), and Hardware-in-the-Loop (HIL) testing to ensure real-time performance. While PIL and HIL are sometimes used interchangeably, HIL is more general and can involve integrating various hardware components, including sensors and actuators, beyond just the processor.</p> <p>This iterative process allows for continuous refinement of both the model and control strategies, ultimately leading to improved accuracy, reduced development time, and cost efficiency. MBD is widely applied in industries such as automotive, aerospace, and robotics, enhancing collaboration among engineers and ensuring compliance with regulatory standards.</p> <p>The diagram below illustrates a comprehensive V-diagram representing the Model-Based Design (MBD) process for control systems, specifically tailored for aerial vehicles.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/MBD-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/MBD-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/MBD-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/MBD.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Model-Based Design" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption text-center">Model-Based Design</div> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="control"/><category term="control"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Model-Based Design for Control Systems]]></summary></entry></feed>